The theme of my talk today is,
موضوع حديثي اليوم هو،
"Be an artist, right now."
"كن فناناً، الآن."
Most people, when this subject is brought up,
معظم الناس، عندما يأتي هذا الموضوع
get tense and resist it:
يتوترون و يقاومون:
"Art doesn't feed me, and right now I'm busy.
" الفن لا يطعمني، و الآن أنا مشغول.
I have to go to school, get a job,
يجب أن أذهب للمدرسة، و أحصل على وظيفة،
send my kids to lessons ... "
أرسل أبنائي لدروس ... "
You think, "I'm too busy. I don't have time for art."
تفكر، "أنا جداً مشغول. ليس لدي وقت للفن."
There are hundreds of reasons why we can't be artists right now.
يوجد مئات الأسباب حتى لا نكون فنانين الآن.
Don't they just pop into your head?
ألا تشغل عقلك الآن؟
There are so many reasons why we can't be,
يوجد العديد من الأسباب حتى لا نصبح فنانين.
indeed, we're not sure why we should be.
فعلاً، نحن غير متأكدين لماذا يجب أن نكون فنانين.
We don't know why we should be artists,
لا نعلم لماذا يجب أن نكون فنانين،
but we have many reasons why we can't be.
لكن لدينا العديد من الأسباب لكي لا نكون كذلك.
Why do people instantly resist the idea of associating themselves with art?
لماذا الناس يقاومون بشكل مستمر فكرة ربط أنفسهم بالفن؟
Perhaps you think art is for the greatly gifted
ربما تعتقد أن الفن للموهبين بشكل كبير
or for the thoroughly and professionally trained.
أو للمدربين بشكل كامل و باحترافية.
And some of you may think you've strayed too far from art.
والبعض منكم يعتقد أنه ضل بعيداً عن الفن.
Well you might have, but I don't think so.
ربما فعلتوا، لكن لا أظن ذلك.
This is the theme of my talk today.
هذا موضوع حديثي لليوم.
We are all born artists.
كلنا ولدنا فنانين.
If you have kids, you know what I mean.
إذا كان لديك أطفال، ستعرف ما أقصد.
Almost everything kids do is art.
تقريباً كل شيء يفعله الطفل هو فن.
They draw with crayons on the wall.
يرسمون بالطبشور على الجدران.
They dance to Son Dam Bi's dance on TV,
يرقصون على رقصة سون دام بي على التلفزيون،
but you can't even call it Son Dam Bi's dance -- it becomes the kids' own dance.
لكن لا تستطيع أن تدعوها رقصة سون دام بي -- تصبح رقصة الطفل نفسه.
So they dance a strange dance and inflict their singing on everyone.
يرقصون رقصات غريبة ويفرضون غناءهم على الجميع.
Perhaps their art is something only their parents can bear,
ربما كان فنهم شيء لا يستطيع أي أحد تحمله ماعدا والديهم،
and because they practice such art all day long,
و لأنهم يمارسون مثل هذا الفن طوال اليوم،
people honestly get a little tired around kids.
الناس بصراحة يتعبون من الأطفال.
Kids will sometimes perform monodramas --
الأطفال أحياناً يؤدون مونودراما --
playing house is indeed a monodrama or a play.
لعب لعبة المنزل فعلا منودراما أو مسرحية.
And some kids, when they get a bit older,
وبعض الأطفال، عندما يصبحون أكبر بقليل،
start to lie.
يبدأون بالكذب.
Usually parents remember the very first time their kid lies.
عادة الوالدين يتذكرون أول كذبة يكذبها طفلهم.
They're shocked.
يتفاجؤن.
"Now you're showing your true colors," Mom says. She thinks, "Why does he take after his dad?"
تقول الأم "الآن أظهرت ألوانك الحقيقية،". تفكر، "لماذا يشبه أبوه؟"
She questions him, "What kind of a person are you going to be?"
تشك فيه، "أي نوع من الأشخاص ستكون؟"
But you shouldn't worry.
لكن لا يجب أن تقلقوا.
The moment kids start to lie is the moment storytelling begins.
في اللحظة التي يبدأ الأطفال في الكذب تبدأ لحظة قول القصة.
They are talking about things they didn't see.
يتكلمون عن أشياء لم يروها.
It's amazing. It's a wonderful moment.
إنه شيء رائع. إنها لحظة مدهشة.
Parents should celebrate.
الوالدين يجب ان يحتفلوا بها.
"Hurray! My boy finally started to lie!"
"هوراي! ابني بدأ بالكذب!"
All right! It calls for celebration.
حسناً! ويتصل ليعلن عن حفل.
For example, a kid says, "Mom, guess what? I met an alien on my way home."
على سبيل المثال، طفل يقول،"ماما، خمني ماذا؟ قابلت كائن غريب في طريق العودة للمنزل."
Then a typical mom responds, "Stop that nonsense."
أم عادية سترد، "توقف عن الهراء."
Now, an ideal parent is someone who responds like this:
الآن، والدين مثاليين هما من يرد بمثل هذا:
"Really? An alien, huh? What did it look like? Did it say anything?
"حقاً، كائن غريب، هاه؟ كيف كان يبدو؟ هل قال شيئاً؟
Where did you meet it?" "Um, in front of the supermarket."
أين قابلته؟" "أمم، أمام السوبرماركت."
When you have a conversation like this,
عندما تتحاورن هكذا،
the kid has to come up with the next thing to say to be responsible for what he started.
الطفل يصبح عليه أن يخترع الشيء القادم ليقوله يجب أن يكون مسؤول عن ما بدأ به.
Soon, a story develops.
قريباً، قصة تتطور.
Of course this is an infantile story,
بالطبع هذه قصة طفولية،
but thinking up one sentence after the next
لكن التفكير بعبارة بعد القادمة
is the same thing a professional writer like me does.
هو نفس الشيء الذي يفعله الكاتب المحترف.
In essence, they are not different.
في الأساس، هم ليسوا مختلفين.
Roland Barthes once said of Flaubert's novels,
رونالد بارت قال مرة عن رواية فلوبير،
"Flaubert did not write a novel.
"فلوبير لم يكتب رواية،
He merely connected one sentence after another.
هو بالكاد ربط عبارة بعد الأخرى.
The eros between sentences, that is the essence of Flaubert's novel."
الفراغات بين العبارات، ذلك أساس رواية فلوبير."
That's right -- a novel, basically, is writing one sentence,
ذلك صحيح -- الرواية، أساساً هي كتابة عبارة،
then, without violating the scope of the first one,
ثم، بدون الخروج عن مجال العبارة الأولى،
writing the next sentence.
نكتب العبارة القادمة.
And you continue to make connections.
وتستمر بوضع ترابط.
Take a look at this sentence:
خذ نظرة على هذه الجملة:
"One morning, as Gregor Samsa was waking up from anxious dreams, he discovered that in his bed he had been changed into a monstrous verminous bug."
"في إصباح يوم من الأيام، أثناء إستيقاظ جورج سامسا من أحلام مربكة، اكتشف أن سريره تغير إلى حشرة دودية وحشية."
Yes, it's the first sentence of Franz Kafka's "The Metamorphosis."
نعم، إنها أول جملة لفرانز كافكا "الانمساخ."
Writing such an unjustifiable sentence
كتابة عبارة مثل تلك غير مبررة
and continuing in order to justify it,
والاستمرار بحيث يستطيع تبريرها،
Kafka's work became the masterpiece of contemporary literature.
عمل كافكا أصبح تحفة في الأدب المعاصر.
Kafka did not show his work to his father.
كافكا لم يُطلع والده على عمله.
He was not on good terms with his father.
لم يكن على اتفاق مع والده.
On his own, he wrote these sentences.
بنفسه، كتب تلك العبارات.
Had he shown his father, "My boy has finally lost it," he would've thought.
هل عرضها على والده، "ولدي أخيراً فقد عقله،" سيفكر هكذا.
And that's right. Art is about going a little nuts
وذلك صحيح. الفن هو حول القليل من الجنون
and justifying the next sentence,
و تبرير العبارة القادمة،
which is not much different from what a kid does.
وهو لا يختلف عما يفعله الطفل.
A kid who has just started to lie
الطفل الذي بدأ بالكذب
is taking the first step as a storyteller.
أخذ أول خطوة كقاص للقصة.
Kids do art.
الأطفال يمارسون الفن.
They don't get tired and they have fun doing it.
لايتعبون و يمرحون أثناء ذلك.
I was in Jeju Island a few days ago.
كنت في جزيرة جيجو قبل أيام قليلة سابقة.
When kids are on the beach, most of them love playing in the water.
عندما كان هناك أطفال على الشاطئ، معظمهم يحبون اللعب بالماء.
But some of them spend a lot of time in the sand,
لكن بعض منهم يحبون قضاء الوقت في الرمل،
making mountains and seas -- well, not seas,
يصنعون الجبال والبحور -- حسناً، ليس البحور،
but different things -- people and dogs, etc.
لكن أشياء مختلفة -- أشخاص وكلاب -- إلخ.
But parents tell them,
لكن الوالدين يخبرونهم،
"It will all be washed away by the waves."
"جميع ماصنعتوه ستغمره موجات البحر ويختفي."
In other words, it's useless.
بكلمات أخرى، إنها بلا فائدة.
There's no need.
لا يوجد حاجة.
But kids don't mind.
لكن الأطفال لايمانعون.
They have fun in the moment
يستمتعون باللحظة
and they keep playing in the sand.
ويستمرون باللعب في الرمل.
Kids don't do it because someone told them to.
لا يفعلها الأطفال لأن شخصاً ما أخبرهم أن يفعلوا ذلك.
They aren't told by their boss
لا يؤمرون من قبل رئيسهم في العمل
or anyone, they just do it.
أو أي أحد، فقط يفعلونها.
When you were little, I bet you spent time enjoying the pleasure of primitive art.
عندما كنتم صغار، أراهن أنكم قضيتم الوقت بالاستمتاع بالفن البدائي.
When I ask my students to write about their happiest moment,
عندما أطلب من طلابي أن يكتبوا عن أسعد لحظاتهم،
many write about an early artistic experience they had as a kid.
العديد يكتب عن تجاربهم المبكرة كأطفال.
Learning to play piano for the first time and playing four hands with a friend,
تعلم البيانو لاول مرة ولعب اليدين الأربعة مع صديق،
or performing a ridiculous skit with friends looking like idiots -- things like that.
أو أداء قصة فكاهية سخيفة مع الأصدقاء حيث نبدو كالأغبياء -- أشياء كهذه.
Or the moment you developed the first film you shot with an old camera.
أو اللحظة التي طورت فيها أول فلم لك بكاميرا قديمة.
They talk about these kinds of experiences.
يتكلمون عن تلك الأنواع من التجارب.
You must have had such a moment.
لابد أن لك مثل تلك اللحظات.
In that moment, art makes you happy
في اللحظة هذه، الفن يجعلك سعيد
because it's not work.
لأنه ليس عمل.
Work doesn't make you happy, does it? Mostly it's tough.
العمل لا يجعلك سعيد، هل يفعل؟ في الغالب هو صارم.
The French writer Michel Tournier has a famous saying.
الكاتب الفرنسي ميشال تورنير لديه قول مشهور.
It's a bit mischievous, actually.
إنها عبثية قليلاً، حقيقة.
"Work is against human nature. The proof is that it makes us tired."
"العمل هو ضد الطبيعة البشرية. البرهان أن العمل يجعلنا متعبين."
Right? Why would work tire us if it's in our nature?
صحيح؟ لماذا قد يتعبنا العمل إذا كان في طبيعتنا؟
Playing doesn't tire us.
اللعب لا يتعبنا.
We can play all night long.
نستطيع أن نلعب طوال الليل.
If we work overnight, we should be paid for overtime.
إذا عملنا ليلة إضافية، يجب أن يدفع لنا للوقت الإضافي.
Why? Because it's tiring and we feel fatigue.
لماذا؟ لأنه متعب ونشعر بالإنهاك.
But kids, usually they do art for fun. It's playing.
لكن الأطفال، عادة يصنعون الفن للمرح. إنه لعب
They don't draw to sell the work to a client
لا يرسمون ليبيعون العمل لزبون
or play the piano to earn money for the family.
أو يعزفون البيانو ليكسبوا النقود لعائلتهم.
Of course, there were kids who had to.
بالتأكيد، يوجد بعض الأطفال الذين اضطروا لذلك.
You know this gentleman, right?
تعرفون هذا الجنتلمان، صحيح؟
He had to tour around Europe to support his family --
كان عليه أن يترحل حول أوروبا ليدعم عائلته --
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart --
وولفغانغ أماديوس موزارت --
but that was centuries ago, so we can make him an exception.
لكن كان ذلك قبل قرون ماضيه، لذا نستطيع جعله استثناء.
Unfortunately, at some point our art -- such a joyful pastime -- ends.
لسوء الحظ، في نقطة معينة فننا -- ياله من وقت ممتع مضى -- ينتهي
Kids have to go to lessons, to school, do homework
الأطفال يجب عليهم أن يذهبوا إلى الدروس، للمدرسة، ليحلوا الواجبات
and of course they take piano or ballet lessons,
و بالطبع يأخذوا دروس بيانو أو باليه،
but they aren't fun anymore.
لكنها لم تعد ممتعة.
You're told to do it and there's competition. How can it be fun?
تؤمر بأن تفعلها وتوجد المنافسة. كيف تصبح ممتعة؟
If you're in elementary school and you still draw on the wall,
إذا كنت في المدرسة الإبتدائية و لازلت ترسم على الجدران،
you'll surely get in trouble with your mom.
ستكون في ورطة مؤكدة مع أمك.
Besides,
أيضاً،
if you continue to act like an artist as you get older,
إذا استمريت بالتصرف كفنان كلما كبرت،
you'll increasingly feel pressure --
ستشعر بالضغط بشكل متزايد --
people will question your actions and ask you to act properly.
الناس ستشك في تصرفاتك و تطلب منك أن تتصرف بشكل مناسب.
Here's my story: I was an eighth grader and I entered a drawing contest at school in Gyeongbokgung.
لديكم قصتي: كنت في الصف الثامن ودخلت مسابقة رسم في مدرسة كيونغ بوك كونغ.
I was trying my best, and my teacher came around
كنت أحاول بافضل ما أستطيع، و أتت معلمتي
and asked me, "What are you doing?"
وسألتني، "ماذا تفعل؟"
"I'm drawing diligently," I said.
قلت "أنا أرسم باجتهاد".
"Why are you using only black?"
"لماذا تستخدم الأسود فقط؟"
Indeed, I was eagerly coloring the sketchbook in black.
فعلاً، كنت ألوّن الكراسة بتلهف باللون الأسود.
And I explained,
و شرحت،
"It's a dark night and a crow is perching on a branch."
"إنها ليلة مظلمة وغراب قابع على الغصن."
Then my teacher said,
عندها معلمتي قالت،
"Really? Well, Young-ha, you may not be good at drawing but you have a talent for storytelling."
"حقاً؟ حسناً، يونغ-ها، ربما لست جيداً في الرسم لك لديك موهبة قص القصص."
Or so I wished.
أو كما تمنيت.
"Now you'll get it, you rascal!" was the response. (Laughter)
"الآن ستفهم، يانذل!" كانت رد الفعل. (ضحك)
"You'll get it!" he said.
قال"ستفهم!".
You were supposed to draw the palace, the Gyeonghoeru, etc.,
كان علينا أن نرسم القصر، الكيونغ هيرو، الخ....
but I was coloring everything in black,
لكن كنت ألوّن كل شيء بالأسود،
so he dragged me out of the group.
لذا أخرجتني من المجموعة.
There were a lot of girls there as well,
كان هناك الكثير من الفتيات ايضاً،
so I was utterly mortified.
كنت أشعر بالذل تماماً.
None of my explanations or excuses were heard,
ولا أي من شروحاتي أو أعذاري تم سماعها،
and I really got it big time.
و أكلتها أكله كبيرة.
If he was an ideal teacher, he would have responded like I said before,
لو كان لدينا الآن معلم مثالي، كان قد رد مثل ما قلت سابقاً،
"Young-ha may not have a talent for drawing,
"يونج-ها ربما ليس لديه موهبة الرسم،
but he has a gift for making up stories," and he would have encouraged me.
لكن لديه موهبة قص القصص،" و أخذ يشجعني.
But such a teacher is seldom found.
لكن مثل هذا المعلم نادراً ما تجده.
Later, I grew up and went to Europe's galleries --
بعد حين، كبرت وذهبت إلى معارض أوروبا --
I was a university student -- and I thought this was really unfair.
كنت طالب جامعي -- وفكرت هذا حقاً غير عادل.
Look what I found. (Laughter)
أنظروا ماذا وجدت. (ضحك)
Works like this were hung in Basel while I was punished
أعمال مثل هذه كانت معلقة في بازب بينما تم عقابي أنا
and stood in front of the palace with my drawing in my mouth.
و إيقافي أمام القصر مع رسمتي في فمي.
Look at this. Doesn't it look just like wallpaper?
انظروا إلى هذه. ألا تبدو مثل ورق الجدران؟
Contemporary art, I later discovered, isn't explained by a lame story like mine.
الفن المعاصر، مؤخراً اكتشفت، لا يشرح بقصة مملة مثل قصتي.
No crows are brought up.
لا غربان تذكر.
Most of the works have no title, Untitled.
معظم الأعمال ليس لها عنوان، بدون عنوان.
Anyways, contemporary art in the 20th century
على أي حال، الفن المعاصر في القرن ال20
is about doing something weird and filling the void with explanation and interpretation --
هو حول القيام بشيء غريب ثم ملئ الفراغ بشرح و تفسير --
essentially the same as I did.
بالضرورة مثل ما فعلت.
Of course, my work was very amateur,
بالتأكيد كان عملي غير ناضج
but let's turn to more famous examples.
لكن لنتحول إلى أمثلة أكثر شهرة.
This is Picasso's.
هذا عمل بيكاسو.
He stuck handlebars into a bike seat and called it "Bull's Head." Sounds convincing, right?
ألصق مقاود على مقعد دراجة و سماها "رأس الثور". يبدو مقنع، صحيح؟
Next, a urinal was placed on its side and called "Fountain".
التالي، مبولة وضعت على الجانب وسميت "نافورة".
That was Duchamp.
ذلك كان دوشامب.
So filling the gap between explanation and a weird act with stories --
إذا ملئ الفارغ بين الشرح و التصرف الغريب بالقصص --
that's indeed what contemporary art is all about.
هذا فعلاً ما يدور حوله الفن المعاصر
Picasso even made the statement,
حتى بيكاسو قال عبارة،
"I draw not what I see but what I think."
"أرسم ليس ما أرى لكن ما أفكر به."
Yes, it means I didn't have to draw Gyeonghoeru.
نعم، يعني أنه لم يكن علي أن أرسم قصر كيونغ هايور.
I wish I knew what Picasso said back then. I could have argued better with my teacher.
أتمنى أني كنت أعرف ما قال بيكاسو في تلك الأيام. كان استطعت أن أناقش معلمي بشكل أفضل.
Unfortunately, the little artists within us
للأسف، الفنانين الصغار داخلنا
are choked to death before we get to fight against the oppressors of art.
خنقوا للموت قبل أن نستطيع أن نحارب ضد طغاة الفن.
They get locked in.
تم القفل عليهم في الداخل.
That's our tragedy.
تلك هي تراجديتنا.
So what happens when little artists get locked in, banished or even killed?
إذا ماذا يحدث عندما يقفل على الفنانين الصغار بداخلنا، ينفون أو حتى يقتلون؟
Our artistic desire doesn't go away.
رغباتنا الفنية لا تذهب.
We want to express, to reveal ourselves,
نريد أن نعبّر، أن نكشف عن أنفسنا،
but with the artist dead, the artistic desire reveals itself in dark form.
لكن مع الفنان الميت، الرغبات الفنية تكشف عن نفسها بصورة مظلمة.
In karaoke bars, there are always people who sing
في غرف الكاريوكي، يوجد دائماً أشخاص يغنون
"She's Gone" or "Hotel California,"
"ذهبت" أو "هوتيل كاليفورنيا"
miming the guitar riffs.
مقلدين نغمات الجيتار.
Usually they sound awful. Awful indeed.
عادة أصواتهم سيئة. فعلاً سيئة
Some people turn into rockers like this.
بعض الاشخاص يتحولون إلى روكر هكذا.
Or some people dance in clubs.
بعض الأشخاص يرقصون في النوادي.
People who would have enjoyed telling stories
الأشخاص الذين استمتعوا بقص القصص
end up trolling on the Internet all night long.
ينتهي بهم المطاف يقضون الليل بطوله على الانترنت .
That's how a writing talent reveals itself on the dark side.
هكذا موهبة الكتابة تكشف نفسها على الجهة المظلمة.
Sometimes we see dads get more excited than their kids
أحياناً نجد الآباء يتحمسون أكثر من أطفالهم
playing with Legos or putting together plastic robots.
يلعبون الليجو أو يركبون الربوت البلاستيكي.
They go, "Don't touch it. Daddy will do it for you."
يقولون، " لا تلمسه. بابا سيصنعه لك."
The kid has already lost interest and is doing something else,
الطفل فقد الإثارة و بدأ يلعب بشيء آخر.
but the dad alone builds castles.
لكن الأب وحده يصنع القصور.
This shows the artistic impulses inside us are suppressed, not gone.
هذا يُظهر أن الإندفاعات الفنية داخلنا مكبوته، لم تذهب.
But they can often reveal themselves negatively, in the form of jealousy.
لكن بإمكانهم في أوقات كثيرة أن يظهروا أنفسهم بشكل سلبي، بصورة غيرة.
You know the song "I would love to be on TV"? Why would we love it?
تعرفون الأغنية "أحب أن أكون في التلفاز"؟ لماذا نحبها؟
TV is full of people who do what we wished to do,
التلفاز مليء بأشخاص يفعلون ما تمنينا فعله،
but never got to.
لكن لم نستطع فعله أبداً.
They dance, they act -- and the more they do, they are praised.
يرقصون، يمثلون -- وكلما فعلوا أكثر، يُمدحون أكثر.
So we start to envy them.
لذا نحسدهم.
We become dictators with a remote and start to criticize the people on TV.
نصبح دكتاتوريون مع جهاز تحكم عن بعد و نبدأ بنقد الأشخاص على التلفاز.
"He just can't act." "You call that singing? She can't hit the notes."
"لا يستطيع أن يمثل". "تسمي ذلك غناء؟ لا تستطيع أن تصل إلى النوتات."
We easily say these sorts of things.
نقول مثل تلك الأشياء بسهولة.
We get jealous, not because we're evil,
نغار، ليس لأننا أشرار،
but because we have little artists pent up inside us.
لكن لأننا نملك فنانون صغار محبسوين داخلنا.
That's what I think.
هذا ما أعتقد.
What should we do then?
لماذا يجب أن نفعل إذا؟
Yes, that's right.
نعم، ذلك صحيح.
Right now, we need to start our own art.
الآن، يجب أن نبدأ فننا الخاص.
Right this minute, we can turn off TV,
فيه هذه اللحظة، نستطيع أن نغلق التلفاز،
log off the Internet,
نسجّل الخروج من الإنترنت،
get up and start to do something.
نقف و نبدأ فعل شئٍ ما.
Where I teach students in drama school,
حيث أعلّم الطلاب في مدرسة الدراما،
there's a course called Dramatics.
يوجد فصل يُسمى التمثيل المسرحي.
In this course, all students must put on a play.
في هذا الفصل، كل الطلاب يجب أن يكونوا مسرحية.
However, acting majors are not supposed to act.
مع ذلك، قسم التمثيل لا يفترض ان يمثلوا.
They can write the play, for example,
بإمكانهم أن يكتبوا مسرحية، على سبيل المثال،
and the writers may work on stage art.
والكتّاب قد يعملون على الفن المسرحي.
Likewise, stage art majors may become actors, and in this way you put on a show.
مثل ذلك، قسم الفن المسرحي قد يصبحون ممثلين، و بهذه الطريقة تصنع عرض.
Students at first wonder whether they can actually do it,
الطلاب في البداية يتسائلون هل يستطيعون فعلها حقاً،
but later they have so much fun. I rarely see anyone who is miserable doing a play.
لكن بعد حين يحظون بالكثير من المتعة. نادراً ما أرى أي شخص يكون بائس أثناء عمل المسرحية.
In school, the military or even in a mental institution, once you make people do it, they enjoy it.
في المدرسة، أو العسكرية أو حتى في المؤسسات العقلية، عندما تجعل الناس يفعلونها، يستمتعون بها.
I saw this happen in the army -- many people had fun doing plays.
رأيت ذلك يحدث في الجيش -- العديد من الأشخاص استمتعوا بعمل المسرحيات.
I have another experience:
لدي تجربة أخرى:
In my writing class, I give students a special assignment.
خلال درس الكتابة الذي أعلّمه، أعطي الطلاب تكليف خاص.
I have students like you in the class -- many who don't major in writing.
لدي طلاب مثلكم في الصف -- العديد ليسوا في قسم الكتابة.
Some major in art or music and think they can't write.
البعض من قسم الموسيقى أو الفن ويعتقدون أنهم لايستطيعون الكتابة.
So I give them blank sheets of paper and a theme.
لذا أعطيهم أوراق فارغة و فكرة رئيسية.
It can be a simple theme:
يمكن أن تكون فكرة بسيطة:
Write about the most unfortunate experience in your childhood.
اكتب عن أكثر تجربة سيئة حدثت في طفولتك.
There's one condition: You must write like crazy. Like crazy!
لكن يوجد شرط واحد: يجب أن تكتب مثل المجنون.مثل المجنون!
I walk around and encourage them,
أمشي في الأنحاء و أشجعهم،
"Come on, come on!" They have to write like crazy for an hour or two.
"هيا، هيا!" يجب أن يكتبوا مثل المجانين لمدة ساعة أو ساعتين.
They only get to think for the first five minutes.
فقط لديهم أول خمس دقائق للتفكير.
The reason I make them write like crazy is because
السبب في أني أجعلهم يكتبوا مثل المجانين هو
when you write slowly and lots of thoughts cross your mind,
عندما تكتب ببطء العديد من الأفكار تمر عليك،
the artistic devil creeps in.
الفنان الشرير ينسل إلى الداخل.
This devil will tell you hundreds of reasons
هذا الشرير سيخبرك بمئات الأسباب
why you can't write:
تمنعك من الكتابة:
"People will laugh at you. This is not good writing!
"الناس سيضحكون عليك. هذه ليست كتابة جيدة!
What kind of sentence is this? Look at your handwriting!"
من أي نوع هذه العبارة؟ أنظر إلى خط يدك!"
It will say a lot of things.
سيقول الكثير من الأشياء.
You have to run fast so the devil can't catch up.
يجب أن تجري بسرعة حتى لا يستطيع الشرير ان يلحق بك.
The really good writing I've seen in my class
الكتابة الجيدة حقاً في صفي التي رأيتها
was not from the assignments with a long deadline,
لم تكن من التكاليف التي تأخذ وقتا طويلا،
but from the 40- to 60-minute crazy writing students did
لكن من الكتابة المجنونة ذات ال 40 - إلى - 60 دقيقة التي فعلوها الطلاب
in front of me with a pencil.
أمامي بقلم الرصاص.
The students go into a kind of trance.
الطلاب يدخلون في نوع من الافتتان.
After 30 or 40 minutes, they write without knowing what they're writing.
بعد 30 أو 40 دقيقة، يكتبون بدون أن يعرفوا ماذا يكتبون.
And in this moment, the nagging devil disappears.
وفي تلك اللحظة، الشرير النقّاق يختفي.
So I can say this:
لذا أستطيع قول هذا:
It's not the hundreds of reasons why one can't be an artist,
إنها ليست المئة سبب التي تجعل الشخص لا يستطيع أن يكون فنان،
but rather, the one reason one must be that makes us artists.
لكن بالأحرى، السبب الوحيد الذي يجعلنا فنانين.
Why we cannot be something is not important.
لماذا لا نستطيع أن نكون شيئاً ما هو شيء غير مهم.
Most artists became artists because of the one reason.
معظم الفنانين أصبحوا فنانين بفضل السبب الوحيد.
When we put the devil in our heart to sleep and start our own art,
عندما نجعل الشرير الذي بداخلنا ينام ونبدأ بفننا،
enemies appear on the outside.
الأعداء يظهرون من الخارج.
Mostly, they have the faces of our parents. (Laughter)
عادة، لديهم أوجه والدينا. (ضحك)
Sometimes they look like our spouses,
أحيانا يكونون مثل أزواجنا،
but they are not your parents or spouses.
لكنهم ليسوا والديك أو زوجك.
They are devils. Devils.
إنهم أشرار. أشرار
They came to Earth briefly transformed
أتوا إلى الأرض متحولين لوقت بسيط
to stop you from being artistic, from becoming artists.
لإيقافكم عن أن تكونوا فنانين، من أن تصبحوا فنانين.
And they have a magic question.
ولديهم سؤال سحري.
When we say, "I think I'll try acting. There's a drama school in the community center," or
عندما نقول، "أعتقد أني سأجرب التمثيل. يوجد مدرسة دراما في المركز الإجتماعي،" أو
"I'd like to learn Italian songs," they ask, "Oh, yeah? A play? What for?"
"أريد أن أتعلم الأغاني الإيطالية،" يسألون، "أوه، ياه؟ مسرحية؟ لماذا؟"
The magic question is, "What for?"
السؤال السحري هو "لأي سبب؟"
But art is not for anything.
لكن الفن ليس لأي سبب.
Art is the ultimate goal.
الفن هو الغاية القصوى.
It saves our souls and makes us live happily.
إنه ينقذ أرواحنا و يجعلنا نعيش بسعادة.
It helps us express ourselves and be happy without the help of alcohol or drugs.
يساعدنا أن نعبر عن أنفسنا و أن نكون سعداء بدون مساعدة الكحول أو المخدرات.
So in response to such a pragmatic question,
لذا كرد على سؤال ذرائعي كهذا،
we need to be bold.
يجب أن نكون جريئين.
"Well, just for the fun of it. Sorry for having fun without you,"
"حسناً، فقط للاستمتاع به. أعتذر لأني أستمتع بدونك،"
is what you should say. "I'll just go ahead and do it anyway."
هو ما يجب أن تقول. " فقط سأستمر و أفعل ما أريد بأي حال."
The ideal future I imagine is where we all have multiple identities,
المستقبل المثالي الذي أتخيله هو حيث جميعنا نملك هويات متعددة،
at least one of which is an artist.
على الأقل واحدة منها هو الفنان.
Once I was in New York and got in a cab. I took the backseat,
مرة كنت في نيويورك و ركبت سيارة أجرة. جلست في المقعد الخلفي،
and in front of me I saw something related to a play.
و أمامي رأيت شيئاً ما مرتبط بمسرحية.
So I asked the driver, "What is this?"
لذا سألت السائق، "ماهذا؟"
He said it was his profile. "Then what are you?" I asked. "An actor," he said.
قال إنه ملفه الشخصي. سألته "إذا ماذا أنت؟". قال"ممثل،".
He was a cabby and an actor. I asked, "What roles do you usually play?"
كان سائق أجرة و ممثل. سالت، "أي الأدوار عادة تلعب؟"
He proudly said he played King Lear.
قال بفخر الملك لير.
King Lear.
الملك لير.
"Who is it that can tell me who I am?" -- a great line from King Lear.
"من الذي يستطيع أن يخبرني من أنا؟" -- سطر عظيم للملك لير.
That's the world I dream of.
ذلك العالم الذي أحلم به.
Someone is a golfer by day and writer by night.
شخص ما حيث يكون لاعب غولف في الصباح و كاتب في الليل.
Or a cabby and an actor, a banker and a painter,
أو سائق أجرة وممثل، عامل بنكي و رسام،
secretly or publicly performing their own arts.
حيث نؤدي فننا الخاص سرياً أو علنياً.
In 1990, Martha Graham, the legend of modern dance, came to Korea.
في عام ، مارثا قراهام، إسطورة الرقص الحديث، أتى إلى كوريا.
The great artist, then in her 90s, arrived at Gimpo Airport
الفنان العظيم، ثم عندها في التسعينات، وصلت إلى مطار جيمبو
and a reporter asked her a typical question:
و المراسلين سألوها السؤال معتاد:
"What do you have to do to become a great dancer?
"ماذا يجب أن تفعل حتى تصبح راقص عظيم؟
Any advice for aspiring Korean dancers?"
أي نصيحة للراقصين الطموحين الكوريين؟"
Now, she was the master. This photo was taken in 1948 and she was already a celebrated artist.
الآن، كانت المعلمة. تلك الصورة أخذت عام 1948 وكانت فنانة معروفة.
In 1990, she was asked this question.
في 1990، سألت هذا السؤال.
And here's what she answered:
وهنا ما جاوبت:
"Just do it."
"فقط افعلها."
Wow. I was touched.
واو. تأثرت.
Only those three words and she left the airport. That's it.
فقط هذه الثلاث كلمات وغادرت المطار. كان ذلك كل شيء.
So what should we do now?
لذا ماذا يجب أن نفعل الآن؟
Let's be artists, right now. Right away. How?
لنكن، فنانين، الآن. مباشرة. كيف؟
Just do it!
فقط افعلها!
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)